...is on all right that's better.
Okay, so, we're just about ready to get started so,
thanks everyone and...thanks that time thanks for taking the time to
...the session today I'm
...and I'm a program manager working on visual studio nineteen you know,
is responsible for building all of the tools for windows stan universal windows
app development and, today I'm going to take the time to talk about
...net primarily and how it relates to building universal windows
appsusing example so just to summarize I've just
to again recapping to primary talk about dot net development in the context of example applications?
I really don't know what the slide does I guess you guys can submit
and evaluation form but I'll skip asked okay, so,
I'm going to make an assumption I'm going to assume that you've already have
the some experience building either of windows a dot one or
of windows phony dot one dot net application and primarily example
dot net application and, I'm going to go a little deeper into dot net
today than stay at the high-level so,
if you have any questions at any point in time and you think I'm going to fast
...please feel free to raise your hand and ask it and I will try to clarify and
...a little bit my objective is that when you walk away from the session you
will have a better understanding of some of the key differences
when it comes to how dot net works when it comes to windows stand universal
...in relation to how it used to work for windows a dot
one-hour windows phony dot one.
So, the key difference and...probably going to spend most of the time talking about
today is dot net native but before I describe some of the benefits and what it
is just I'm just curious how many of you have heard of...native before?
And, that's actually...that's actually a pretty good chunk...audience so just for the remainder the
folks limiting a couple of minutes to recap what is dot native it's
over next generation of compiler technologies for dot net that allows us
to compile dot net applications down to the actual bits be that x eighty-six
rx sixty-four arm in the cloud it allows us to provide a
converged consistent set of experiences across all devices that run windows
down and, it also allows us to use some of the great work we
have done in our cplus-plus technologies in our back-end to bring that to a dot
net developer we've done a lot of work to make sure that the optimizations that we do
for your cplus-plus code are actually pretty good and this is an opportunity very
bringing that to you as well the...developer.
So, you might ask the question why dot net native and,
there are multiple facets of this particular question that I'm going to try to
sort of address here the very first thing is mobile apps today and
absolute particularly build for windows...universal windows apps for windows
...they have a certain set of requirements that's different than what
...you would have expected from a typical within thirty do style desktop application let's say a
...application or something like that the
...users the uses of your application expect something,
you know, for from these apps and some of them are fast out of time if you're
app doesn't really startup within a particular duration take
...let's say five hundred milliseconds your user is going to walk away so,
with dot non-native we have the technology and reeve bringing it to you to help improve
startup times with hopefully very little work on your end the reason why we are able to achieve
of fast app startup time is because we're trying to...completely so
just-in-time compilation will not happen on a device if you're using dot non-native and,
that's one of the reasons whythe apps are faster and they also start...as well now
...added benefit of not having jet is that you're doing less work on the
cpu rate everything is happening in the cloud before that consumer even
gets the app that has the added benefit that you know,
because the cpu is getting use less there's a little bit more savings in terms of
battery life the battery life is also getting a boost because of dot native in
In our labs we have been using a number of the apps that you folks have built today just
...out the technology and try to see how it works for
existing apps we have noticed up to sixty percent of savings...doing a
...startup and of course these numbers will really very if you take your hello
world application that doesn't really do much you probably won't see as big of...but the more complex the
more functionality it has the better the savings that can potentially be by using dot
...and then...for...seeing improvements somewhere in the ranger forty percent as well so again I want to
be caveat thing this by clearly saying it depends on the kind of application and, the more complex to
add the better the savings there will be...important characteristic of these mobile
...they should not be using a lot of memory the working set requirements like
especially in devices that are very little ram is actually pretty stringent so,
with...also able to address this problem to a certain extentthe
optimizations we do on the compiler side to takeout types and properties and
evens that you really probably don't even need for the functionality of application means
you're working set is probably going to be better at the end of the day by using dot non-native
...again in our in our labs we have been doing desks against
real-world apps and we have seen savings up to thirty-plus and on this front as well
...native helps improve our performance in a number of phase.
Another big reason and, you have been hearing about this throughout this
...this adaptive apps adoptive apps allow us to sort of okay,
so, windows is going to sort of start bringing innovations in terms of new api
...functionality to you very quickly you as a developer have to start thinking
about how you manage this in terms of let's say you get an sdk every few months how do you
...and app that leverages functionality in this sdk in a light up fashion where you
sort of like go and adaptor application to provide the users of your application
better functionality as new and your...similarly not all api is
that windows provides are going to be available on all devices there are going to be device specific
aps that are either of available only on the desktop
our mobile how do you think about lighting up functionality on
...for an application that only runs in such a device
...is adaptive code the...the screen the...over there I'm
...my apologies if it's not really clear at the back of the room it's the pattern that you would
...use a lot when you're building a universal windows app very will sort of
...for the presence of an api and then you will execute that line of code
when that api doesn't really, you know,
...can be confident that the api does exist the problem with this line of code is
...you talk about dot net apps running on top of windows a dot one this particular line
of code would have crashed your application and reason for that as we would just this
code which is just-in-time compile this code on the device the...
would not exist anybody...get...type...exception our method not found exception so
on so forth...because we are avoiding jet completely you're able to
write this line of code and executed on the target device without crashing so this allows us to
...allows you to do is use a very common coding pattern windows stan and use it
in a very natural way if...didn't have this capability you'd have to do some
advanced refactoring operations hide this all in behind interfaces
call those interfaces so on so forth there's a very natural way of writing code
...native we bring this capability of the document developer as well.
And, finally faster...there's a problem that we have been struggling for some
time now historically we have a very tight coupling with windows and dot net like
...think about windows a dot a dot...the first version of windows a that came out we had
a set of api and we sort of bunch them together into a reference said call dot net
core for five and that's the that's the one that you're using for building a windows a
...windows they dot one we got a bunch of feedback from folks and we added a bunch of
you api is the sort of revision that...all windows fold-out five dot
one the problem of these monolithic references that you sort of add your project is
we are tied to sort of the windows update cadence like it's very hard for us to innovate on the
...side...that in terms of like libraries
and functionality or even in terms of visual studio debugging experiences because we really expect
to operating system to have an update cycle before those api
is can be available to you that's one of the things that we want to sort of try to sort of
...thing and see how we can do better so
...native because you're sort of compiling the statically linking in the
entire framework into application what...means is you kind of control what
your application references and you control what sort of functionality do want to bring to the
consumer you don't really have to wait for windows of data push out a new version of
dot net before you can sort of take advantage of that so we expect universal windows apps to sort of
take digg benefit of this feature and get more and more functionality either
...you get that we will sort of publish more and
more libraries and functionality to the user withoutwithout actually waiting for windows
update of course windows update will never breaker application because
...application is really self-contained it contains all of the dot net code that it needs to
run and doesn't depend on a system-wide dot net an update even for that?
So, one thing like...you guys know that we have been actually pushing out dot net binary
...to your devices, you know, over the past.
Couple of months actually here the absolutely here these are some of the apps that, you know,
we have already like pushed out do you guys by running...running with dot
...in the cloud so for
these apps what we've done is we have sort of taken the apps from the store run...
native to chain and then push did you guys so you're actually using these...for example,
the calendar on windows phone is already...the reason why we did this is want to get
similar confidence around like this particular scenario everyone to make sure that
apps don't really break and we sort of like transform them from, you know,
msi...dot...so...a technology that we are
looking for a while and we have already big to a certain extent and now we're ready to bring
...vast to the vast...of developers out there which leads us to this statement.
All universal windows than dot net apps that you will deliver to your client
...the windows store or even why...enterprise side load scenario will have to be
compile the darpa native so it becomes really common place for everyone out there and,
it's important to understand how you should approach this and how you should think about dot
...in that context?
So, now let's take a moment to think about the developer workflow and how you how this
developer workflows changes slightly when you bring dot non-native into the makes
...just like before you can continue to
...your code in your dot favorite dot...be that csharp...we
suppose dot...for both of those languages so that really doesn't change similarly you know,
you would have...debug and, you know, code your application using the debug configuration
...that doesn't really change either you continue to sort of push out your apps to multiple devices
be that phones are tablets or pc's nothing really changed from that perspective
as well what really is an important difference between windows a dot one and windows
stand universal apps development is the
release configuration because when you build an application with
...configuration visual studio by default we're turning on dot
native as the technology that...the particular code base and it's
and it's really important and this is where I'm going to keep repeating throughout the session today
it's really important that you...application frequently and periodically...release
we'll talk about how this changes in a second we look at what's going on behind the scenes yes sir?
Yeah, let me repeat the question great
...that question when I take a look the question is you've got a lied when you said,
you know, your app is not going
to have any jet crashes when you're doing debug how do you actually handle that when
you're testing this application...a device and api is not present answer that question for sure
creating packages the stores the same the workflow in visual
studios identical there are some differences in the packages that you build as
debugging release and will articulate that as well but as a developer hopefully that is extremely
...to you are now here's where the
interesting part comes online when you upload your packages to the store
...uploaded sms il and behind-the-scenes on in the
cloud will run dot non-native on your store submitted packages convert them to dot
native before they are delivered to the client now there are a few reasons why run
...native on the in the cloud as opposed to use submitting cognitive packages directly
one of the primary reasons is should there be you know, security vulnerability
are should there be a better optimization technologies that we want to sort
of innovate on our should there be you know,
compatible changes we want to make we can recompile your app and submitted down to the client without
you even knowing about it now of course you should be assured that will guarantee compatibility in this case and
one break your app but having the ability to compile and then sort of
target even newer process architectures is actually really important and this is one of
the reasons why we sort of do cloud compilation in on the
dot native side instead of use submitting those packages to the store and like you said, you know,
when you consumer downloads those packages they are
...native compiled and they are not msi...anymore?
So, without said let's switch over the visual studio and try to
answer the question that you just...in addition to more so.
...is...text very visible at the back of the other room?
Now oebps this is always a problem because if I
could do big will studios ui starts looking not-so-good but I'll try.
Well, because I'm not really going to use the text editor I'm actually going to use the rest of the
...user experience but I'll improve vote.
I'm actually going to use everything outside of a text editor more than anything else but you know,
I'll fix them...
So, text editor goes to sixteen but more importantly the
is that terrago that goes to let's say for dean.
That better okay thank you another item to much
...worry about that.
So, let's take a quick to rough you know, how
...native comes into the picture in visual studio over
here debug configuration release configuration remains the same you must be very familiar these concepts when
you upload and upload your app to the store you have to build
as release we continue to support both of those configurations if you look at the target
...architectures new developer will immediately jump and say where is my any cpu and
we'll talk about that in a second but generally you can build your application as x eighty-six arm rx
sixty-four and then as new part cross architectures come online they'll be added onto this
list as well nothing really changes from that perspective let's take a quick look at the
project properties themselves which is the more interesting part?
Over the last couple days...been talking about adaptive apps and how you think about getting access to
new api is to get access to new vin arty api is you will need
to acquire new version of windows sdk and then targeted
...this drop down we...had multiple sessions
...lapse where people have talked about targeting and I'm not going to go to the details
but assume like you download en-us began a new entry shows down here and you just continue to
sort of like just pick that up and you get access to the api is
that particular sdk exposes the main version drop down allows you to sort
of specify the universal windows platform that you required for application
...if you specify a particular version here you can be guaranteed that
the application will not be offered to a device that's running and version that's older
than what you specified so this allows you to constrained this...and max values as we call
it allow you to constrain the range of windows devices that you want to target...it's
in the in your best interest that you target the widest possible range of devices
but the same time you also have to be realistic about the test matrix and...I
think about it so that's really a choice that you can make and I'm going to go too much into the details here because we have
discussed this in prior sessions but interesting part really
...the build options and ...there is debug
and release but if you take a look at the debug configuration there's a new check box here compile with dot
...to change and that check boxes stoned off by default by the way if you have used a
prior cp of the...native tools you would half how to slightly different workflow
it's actually much better integrated now you really don't have to install anything separate
it's all integrated into this one check box and this is the pretty much the only check box that you have to
our deal with for the most part now if I go
...switch the configuration to release that's when
you will see that the check boxes on and what that really means is when I'm building my app as...building...the
release configuration I'm going to compile with the data native to change so that's where most of the work
is happening relative to what the big differences between windows eight and windows
...so let's go...debug first and take a look at what's going on behind the scenes?
Just...for a quick second.
The abilene runs.
We're not going to go...much of the debugging experience though off the bat you will see some of the experiences like
the ui debugging tools and things like that have a session dedicated to the visual studio
goodness tomorrow so I'm not going to go too much into any of those experiences today so,
let's stop debugging and look at what actually happened behind-the-scenes that's where most of
interesting ...
So, if I go to an open mics eighty-six debug package and crack
open the manifest the very first thing you will notice is whoops negative right.
Sorry I got the
...if I open of the manifest that text is visible back there right
ok great so the first thing you'll notice is we have transform the manifest
slightly between what you have in your project and what's generated
have generated and entry called package dependency and, what this is
...we are basically taking a dependency on a core clr framework package ...
to put this in other ways your application is running against a sort of like a private version of
the course clr when we when you actually
...this application to a device we are going to push the course
clr to the device before the application actually executes so the let me say this
another way of course clr we think is primarily a debugging scenario and
hence it doesn't make sense for windows devices generally where space
...footprint and things like that are important to carry the course clr...so,
we do have to push the course...as a part of the visual
studio debugging experiences and that's what this is another way to think about the says
...start bringing more and more changes to the
course clr in terms of visual studio debugging experiences much more rapidly because now
we are just deploying course...to any device that we want to debug the app against?
The other transformation that's worth calling out is we have we have changed your
executables slightly to actually use shadow executable what the
shadow executable does is...all it does is a very thin-layer that boots of the course...and
then your code that goes with it nothing really changed my perspective you probably won't even notice this
...I describe what's going on your debugging experience and
...experience remains the same everything, you know,
there should be no difference at all just I want to show you how course clr comes into the picture?
Now you ask me a good question like how do you prevent you know, jet failures from happening because
what's happening is we're taking this code and executing on a mobile device or a desktop device
...that particular api doesn't exist on the desktop device the way we do that is the
...metadata folder that exists here what we do is
we push what we call a union metadata file to every device that
your currently debugging think about this union metadata file as containing all of in
...dives that you ever you know,
could potentially have access to in your application so this particular
metadata file contains all of the types and properties that could
ever exist at that point in time as your developing application by pushing this file over to
the device the jitters actually going to use this
metadata to resolve itself and it's going to prevent the crash from happening
...the same time if you do and adaptive check you say hey he does this particular if
something exists that check will still return the right valid value and you'll be able to
get the exact same functionality so this particular metadata file we are preventing
both the digit failure as well as we are actually giving you the right behavior from a
debugged perspective so you can correctly diagonals issues and functionality...application?
The other thing that's really important word calling out
you cv copied a lot of references in geopackage and that's intentional like
I said before when we talk about dot non-native you're sort of statically linking in your entire framework
into application very similar to a cplus-plus application so,
when you actually think about uploading this app to the store to store has no idea as to what you
built against and it's really important for us to have a contained package that contains all of the
meta data that you upload to the store that's what this packages and contains every
single framework reference that you could potentially...using your application it also means we can ship
...your versions of the framework packages and
the allows and you can continue to use them without having to wait for a whole windows...cycled the
...faster cadence thing that we just talked about at the beginning of the presentation?
that's how the debug workflow works before I switch to release any questions.
Yes.
Yeah, so, the question is this going to increase the size application on the answer is yes but we have some
techniques to avoid that when I do the release configuration you will see an increase and I'll talk
about what we're going to do to make sure that we don't have that problem so yes you're right you're statically linking
in...the same time we...ways to...problem as well yes.
So, the question is why would I want to do this where
...doing something that's not very close to, you know,
the release behavior so one thing is we have done a lot of work to make sure that bonuses and
us your debug behavior and release behavior in our best interest that
...close to each other and we will not guaranteed but
we've done a lot of work to make sure that that's the case the thing why you don't want to use
dominate of all the time is that to chain takes a while to run and you'll see that when I'm doingthe release
...you don't want to be sort of like taking that
...every time you're sort of debugging your application you only productive because that's the promise of dot
net quick bailed run...to sort of like make sure
that productivity is retained by the same time we also realize that you're actually changing the bits
and review and...it's important that you in calculate this practice of frequently
destin release bits but the same time you absolution feel confident that
you're testing mostly against debug bits otherwise...productivity is hampered and,
you know, that's a promise...to give you from that perspective ok.
So, let's go to switch to release and build
and run this application like I said, you know,
it's going to take a while it's going to take about forty five to fifty seconds and,
that's one of the things that, you know, is really important for us to go fix and we're working on some of
the solutions...the same time it's actually doing a lot
of work behind-the-scenes so you should expect this to be absolutely slower than debug
...for sure right so that's what we're doing but the same time currently
this-is going-to-take about forty five fifty seconds while the
...is happening we can get it's already starting to
produce some artifacts and we can go take a look at those so let's go to an open the
release for now and see what's going on that's first open the manifest file
and you'll notice that now there are no more changes like if you look at the dependency section
it's empty and it has no dependencies on any course clr framework package
...your manifest is not exactly the same as you are specified in your source project just
transform to add version information and things like that it's also worth calling out at the bottom
of the manifest we added some extra meta data this has no impact on the functionality of
application that basically tells what the version of the tool chain is the idea of compiler
app that what this allows us to do is in the cloud match-up the exact same to
chain and make sure that the bits that we generate in the cloud are identical to what you actually tested
...it also allows us to ship newer versions of the to chained better improvements
and optimizations and, you can do that all out of band without actually having
to wait for some synchronization between windows and
...studio...dot nineteen so there is what we have done there as well so let's ignore
the debugging experience because it's very similar it's more interesting to look at some of the other
artifacts as well if you look at the app exporter it contains some more
dls than what's the final...not done with this we're not done with our...of this product so,
I'm going to just switch over to you know, and, app...that I cleaned up manually just you can get an idea of
what it looks like and here's what it is actually extremely clean and simple there is nothing
thing no magic here at all there's the manifest but here's the
large dl that you just talked about it's about nine about eight megs and,
then there is a very thin executable as well
...a couple of very small clr runtime staked...
epics package now you might be worried about eight nb you know, statically
laying library that...and I'll talk about what we're doing to mitigate that?
that's one of artifacts that we produce today when you run dot...chain I'll talk about other medications we plan and,
we get to that...second and, everything else is actually exactly what you'd expect
in app expected any questions so far yes sir.
...so you're talking about post...modem debugging like the user
going to crash and I'll talk about that...absolutely I got that.
Ok, so, let's switch back to...for a second before we come back to showing another part of the workflow and,
do a quick summary because we talked about a lot of things ...
you can do you build your application in your language of your choice csharp avi no problem...build
an run your application as debug and the big differences here...using the course
clr for debugging your application we do have a metadata file that we generate
and we keep it updated with all is decays they could ever install in the machine so
that when you're testing your application you don't run into any jet failures and
then of course would copy all of the...references indeo package as well when you're doing testing your
application that's when you're running with a dot native to ching the packages that you submit
...the store there is someinformation some knowledge that you need to xavier which
we'll talk about in the later part of the section but, generally a workflows the same you'd continue to upload the app
...upload files to the store that contain various
architectures and you'd continue to site load if you're an enterprise customer
...as you guys heard we did a lot of work to make side loading a lot more easier...windows
stem you'd continue to use the app x back edge to...low to the right device
...enterprise scenario and the rest of that we already talked about like the store compiles the app
...with a dot...to change before it sends
a down to the client the only thing I want to call out from the perspective of
developer workflow that you should be aware off in visual studio in our packaging
wizard you can specify...specific dr policy of the company that
you're working for the one change that we're making
...windows stan is you can no longer use the revision field...field which is the one that's
highlighted on the screen is going to be blog from you from being use and reason for that as
...said the store is going to compile other
revisions without you probably not knowing for extreme cases let's say not in the
more common scenario and we want to have some capability to version that package that your
...the...gets from the store so you can continues the first three fields
...liking just don't
...afford field many uploaded to the store because that's going to be reserved by the store yes sir?
Yeah, you can use so,
when you say auto increment we are now I'm just going one field to the left and we
can auto increment the third field...sort of the fourth field?
Redundant work and just let me
...the question can use asterisk for the third feel now yes you can?
Well, that include.
That's a good question I don't know...question is will be automatically standard with
the day-time of the compile step ...actually don't know the answer to that maybe I'll
follow up on that particular question offline but I'm sure that you cannot
do increment that I just don't know what the characteristics of the default value are.
And, then like...said when you consumer download the...they will get...packages yes sir.
The one that you're not supposed to dutch.
You start you put zero there and you're done.
Yeah,...and I mean I don't know the I hope we don't have that many of them but.
I don't know the...value to be honest with you.
The question is what's the max value that field and my answer is I don't know but I'll definitely,
you know, follow-up on that question as well.
Now you might say...love mining cpu and that's a valid feed like I've been
following twitter feedback and things like that and this comes up and,
I acknowledge that like I mean this is feedback of looking for...from you guys if you
think this is a significant hindrance...of workflow we'd love to hear feedback and
do better that's certainly something that you're on the watch for but...rationale for
this is two-fold one of them one of that is there's a lot of technical complexity in doing that but
that aside like I said it's really important that the dominate...you tester application against the real
device on the real architecture as opposed to any cpu with sort of fakes with
the preferred thirty two-bit flag or something like that so it's so,
that's one of the reasons why we wanted to sort of go out there without any cpu see
what people think and then come back and sort of like, you know,
you know, if that's a significant workflow locker we can sort of look into addressing that as well
one thing owner...if you are library author and there are some of
...for you the workflow doesn't really change you can continue to shape your any cpu
binarybecause it's up to the developer consumes the binary to sort of go compile that down to the
specific art architecture so from a library other perspective you can continue to do
business as usual and continue to ship your any cpu binary is out there it's the it's on the
developer was consuming that this...is on?
Done a little bit about packaging but I wanted to sort of there're
...of key gorgeous that you should be aware off and ...like throw it out
there one is debug packages you can never submitted them to the store and that's.
Always been the case because windows...education kid will fail those the debug app
expectations are compile with microsoft I'll there's no changes you know,
that's the case was there before...the same today we don't always also generate an app
x upload file because we want to make sure that you...and there is no
...submission scenario debug workflow and hence there is no reason why we should...should generate and
...upload releases where the interesting ...happen when you build release
...you know, package using a packaging wizard will generate actually both...access
will generate an dot native affects...messiah lap x the reason why we do both is
...think enterprise side loading is a common scenario and please do not side load
and messiah lap x back edge always...load and dot net native
epics package because things like adaptive code will crash if you never if you
side loaded...messiah lap...to devices that don't have api when you
...you uploading to the store we do all the work to make sure that the package that-you
upload to the store the epics upload file contains the right bits which is the msi lap expected
...done all this work to make sure that we...on the right path but it's really important
to keep in mind that you shouldn't...go inside load and msi lap
is epics package in an enterprise scenario so you should be careful about that?
Ok.
So, here's another topic that I'm going to throw out there you know,
that sort of has kind of important runtime directives
what runtime directives runtime directives are sort of hints
...dominate of to...to sort of
change the optimization strategy little bit by default ninety percent if
you out there probably don't have to worry about this we do the right thing by default ...are
...policies conservative what we mean by that is by default
will retain all of the types and properties and meta data...you might likely
see slightly larger binary but that's probably the right balance for most
of you users out there that are a few of you'll probably want to eke out that every
last bit of performance are application and that's where you need to pay attention to this particular
workflow which I'll show in a quick second you
use runtime directives to declare what types you want us to keep and what types and properties
...namespaces and things like that you want us to drop you have the flexibility just sort
of say drop everything in which case hopefully...is not really functional that point but you
can also specifically tell us what specific namespaces and types to keep let's say you're using
...string based api how do we know what to keep and what
...throw if you want to sort of...optimize are all the way through so that you
want is advanced reflection...and scenarios...have to worry about this and, you know,
make changes...thing on a...dominate of...support reflection that's not really, you know,
the issue the issue year as when we run the optimize are we need to make sure that we
...your meta data so you reflection can succeed?
One important...for control library authors make sure that your control library contains
...resource that specifies this...make sure that it contains and
...dot xml that can have a conservative policy that's fine but needs to be there because
...user could be actually a guy who wants to sort of get real
performance out of application they could strip down everything accidentally if you don't actually you know,
and, they don't know the details of your library what...libraries doing if
...libraries doing advance reflection and things like that you should give us this hand
...we can do the right thing again like I said if you think that this thing is you know, a
little bit more complex that's fine most of you probably don't have to deal with it let me show quick demo
of what kind of vince you can get if you sort of care about it so let me go switch
back to visual studio.
And, take a look at
a sample project so in this particular project ava control library
an application it's kind of a fake scenario just to sort of you know,
make the point control library has to controls a
data grid and chart in my application I only care about using the
charred control I could never care less about the data grid that's the scenario trying to sort of
...by default if I
...this application remember what I said we use a very conservative policy and retain all of the
meta data so if I go back to my application and I'm not going to spend the time to build this again
with the native I already have a prebuilt package so here's my
...package and here's the dl that I get as a result of that package that I
just build it's about just like before it's about eight megs.
Now let's say I really care about the scenario and I...to sort of make it smaller and, you know, you know,
monkey with the setting more than what I, you know,
I really care about the perf here so let's go and take a look at this file default dot
...dot xml which is something we add to your every project out there if I
...and...you will see that by default...entry in here which is what I said
...conservative policy keep everything retain everything don't change you know,
just keep all metadata and reflection information
and implementation around you can change this so let's say go and common this out.
And, common this other line back in.
Well, this is now we're telling the...or to sort of only retain metadata about the
chart control and implementation and not worry about the data grid at all if I build
and run this application with the dominate...to ching and take a look at what I get as a result of
thatyou'll see that's about a meg less now how can one type result...one
...saving that's because you change the policy pretty aggressively
you change from retain everything to just retain the charred control I can sort of
fine-tuned this further and further but you can get the point like you could choose to sort of
...the optimize if you want to do but,
for the most part it should do the right thing out-of-the-box?
So, what some of the best practices that you should follow if you're building a dot...
application or in particular of universal windows application because all of them are going to be done native
the primarily developer application using debug but make sure you periodically
...application using releases well-known defer the whole thing to the very
and because then it gets a little bit more tricky periodically keep testing application
and release now like I said we are done a lot of work to make sure that the difference in
behavior between debugging releases not much but just in case you do run into a problem one
way that you can probably make for ok the first thing is just
as email so we'd love to hear your feedback and make sure that we take a look and, you know, make sure that, you know,
you don't have to worry about and it's our problem but just in case you are curious and sort of
...investigate this one technique could be do you turn on dot native
in a debug build using the check box that I showed
at the beginning of the presentation they'll probably give you some more information that you can use to better
diagonals such issues but we really hope you don't have to do this submitting
...to the store the most common scenarios to use the epics upload file we do all of the right
things for you but just in case you're interested in submitting individual
...access to the store which is also many people do that as well you could you should definitely make
sure you turn off the flag for building...dot native create a custom configuration and
...of this flag and then submit...I'll package to the store?
Like I said there is there is there's a bunch of...already starting to do on the team between now and
...to improve the experience primarily around the throughput of the bailed as well as
...some of this will get to somevery soon some of this will keep working on
improving and delivering to you as quickly as we can the way we're going to reduce the
size of the dl that you saw the and...megs is we are taking some common
parts of the framework that everyone is going to likely use and re factor that into
a framework package so your application will contain libraries that we don't
think that are ask common statically...and it
also container reference to a framework package that contains the more common functionality so that
we will be able to make sure that your application doesn't contain the entire
framework statically linkedin it's a balance between the most common use cases and we have
lot of data on that versus you know,
what you specifically need and things like that so that's
the by using that technique will be able to control the size of the dl on the package?
Yeah, so, the question is will run into versioning issues with what you reference
...the beginning representation no because the way...do this how
should I says the reason why you run to versioning primarily is because
we're sort of tied into like the windows update cadence in this case it's a framework package
it can be updated in the store at any point as long as that framework package keeps growing
your...just downloads and...washing the framework package and it's done versus an older version favor
packages are side-by-side in the store right so
you will download the right version of the framework package depending upon what references you have any a
...compile-time and that they will be able to make sure that you know,
different apps that have different requirements continue to get the right
bits that they need to execute the functionality?
There are a few...experiences
...this one ...post modem debugging so this is the one that the german
...was asking this is very our app crashes on a device that you don't
...and how do you actually debug this sort of a crash you get a pbr you get a crash
...what you do with it the best practices of course apply maintain
folks of your source code right that's the way you would independent of
...native you really need to maintain a match
imagine bb and source code combination so keep that in mind that doesn't really change
...distorting to make the pcbs available to you will be able to go to the della
proposal and download the pbs and that's the way you would sort of like debug the applications
...would load the pcbs from the ones that you downloaded from the store and then a for coffee
...source code using the to you should be able to debug or at least get a call stack from
the customer application?
Yes, that's correct the question is if...five versions of your apple...dying will they be
five pbs correct and that's the case today as well like if you have five version
your application if you want to get the...
The best debugging experience you should have...versions of
pcbs as well of course source code hasn't changed significantly you may get lucky but,
for the most part you do have five you know,...even today.
Yes, the question is if we do and if you if the so,
the question is if the automatically do rebuild in the cloud for you will we get a different set of
bb answer is yes we don't think this automatic rebuild
is that common a scenario we just have that mechanism in place to sort...address some eventual
...but, yes, we will get you pcbs for that particular.
That's a good question...you get notified when we do and auto rebuild.
I don't have a good answer to that I hope so.
Darden native has some vs integration you know,
backlog that we haven't really addressed the one that you'll probably
care about most is antigen continue you do have to do a and by the way we
just added in continue for cplus-plus when like envious twenty fifteen or something like that
didn't continue doesn't work for dot native apps it does work for debug when you're doing course
...so like that's what I said you should primarily...your debug loop
using course clr because that's going to the best most productive environment but,
we don't support it and continue for dot native things like obfuscate shun and deleterious and just my
code also don't work but, all of these of course work just fine for debug?
Dot net framework evolution...a question that came up like a couple
dimes earlier this week like how do we think about bringing innovation to-you quickly.
Now the way to think about this as the set of api is that we're giving you for windows
...is the same as a set of aps that...for windows a dot one
...one important in clarification all api will work and all devices which means
that...cf which is a question that we get all the time windows communication
foundation works on windows phone as well right so well I like that.
So, that's one clarification but that's not the whole story because that's the story that we're going to give you
...in parallel we're working to sort of delaware newer and
your libraries why'd you get going forward so we'll bring you implementations of
your features and functionality that you guys are asking why and you get
...you already see some of the examples likeif you take a particular the default project templates
in visual studio we already have first few examples where we have system humor x, for example,
including a default template will start adding more and more surface area...your projects based on
where you guys need you know, over time as new get deliverables and that allows us
...the agile and quick and get gets things out
to-you quickly there's one last point I wanted to make which is about consuming libraries and there's a question we get
a locked when we are when our internal...of building apps what's
the story for potable class libraries and what...how do you think about conceiving native references
in application potable class libraries we are working to add windows
stand support of course but keep in mind that potable class libraries that
will build for windows eight and windows a dot one and windows one-dot one should just work as
is like zooming you so, one important caveat as with windows a dot
one and windows a phony dot one we added supports of in rd to very
potable class library so if you go and call into of ninety-eight the
...that doesn't exist on a device now that is not something much we can do about
but that's should be a very isolated rare case so far the most part
existing pc I'll should just working your windows...application?
Dot non-native references
are native references you should be able to add either an existing windows a
...one of windows phony dot one native reference the just do
a managed application and be able to use at the only gotcha is you should also
add a reference to the visual studio twenty thirteen crt.
...application in addition to the native reference because keep in mind that these are the allows the
role compiled with a different crt right so you do need to add a reference to the
crt the good news is you can continue to...of use both
...references together so you can have an app that's using of windows a
dot one component with the visual studio twenty thirteen crt and the same app can also
usewindows universal component...with registry...twenty fifteen crt so that should all be pretty
seem less just keep that in mind we're adding references.
Like I said, you know, the if there's one called to action that,
you know, I would like to sort of your feedback if you take a
nap negative universal windows app and if you're seeing a difference and
behavior between debug and release would love to hear from you a sap so we can go
and address those our goal is to make it such that there should be no
differences at all so please do let us know and these are the to aliases you can use
data native at microsoft-dot-com please do send your mail
with a hopefully reproduction of the problem and we'll...and look at that
all of the stuff that we talked about specifically runtime directives all documented.
Like I said we focus primarily on like
...native today there is another part of visual studio specifically around rich
...tooling...building for universal windows apps my session tomorrow we'll go deep into that
...just don't have enough time to touch on that level of detail today I'll take you through a
tour of all of the unique experiences for universal windows
apps in registry twenty fifteen tomorrow at around noon or something like that there
is a number of sessions we did like the lap around dot net should give you the big-picture of all the things that we're doing
...dot net that's a good session to take a look at but,
these are some of the resources that you can also sort of used to learn more about this experience
what that said I'll open up the flow to questions but more importantly
do take the time to evaluate the session your feedback is really useful we really appreciate
the time that you took become like six pm today or something like that but again
thank you and let-me know if you have any questions?